<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML">
<section id="connection-element">
  <title>The connection element information item</title>
  <para>
    Connection element information items (referred to in this specification as
    connection elements) are element information items in the CellML 1.1 or CellML
    1.2 namespaces with local name equal to connection. CellML Processing software
    MUST support both forms, but SHOULD generate connection elements in the CellML 1.1
    namespace.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Specific information items when in CellML 1.2 namespace</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every connection element MUST contain a component_1 attribute in the
          empty namespace.  The value of the component_1 attribute MUST
          be a valid CellML Identifier. The value of this attribute MUST be equal
          to the name attribute on a component or import component element in
          the CellML Infoset.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every connection element MUST contain a component_2 attribute in the
          empty namespace.  The value of the component_2 attribute MUST
          be a valid CellML Identifier. The value of this attribute MUST be equal
          to the name attribute on a component or import component element in
          the CellML Infoset.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every connection element MUST contain one or more map_variables
          element (<xref linkend="map-variables-element" />).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Specific information items when in CellML 1.1 namespace</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every connection element MUST contain exactly one element with local
          name map_variables in the CellML 1.1 namespace, and that element shall
          in turn have two attributes:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The component_1 attribute in the empty namespace. The value of
                the component_1 attribute MUST be a valid CellML Identifier. The
                value of this attribute MUST be equal to the name attribute on a
                component or import component element in the CellML Infoset.
                Component_1 attributes SHALL be treated in the same way as if they
                appeared on the connection element in the CellML 1.2 namespace.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The component_2 attribute in the empty namespace. The value of
                the component_2 attribute MUST be a valid CellML Identifier.
                The value of this attribute MUST be equal to the name attribute
                on a component or import component element in the CellML Infoset.
                Component_2 attributes SHALL be treated in the same way as if they
                appeared on the connection element in the CellML 1.2 namespace.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every connection element MUST contain one or more map_variables
          elements (<xref linkend="map-variables-element" />).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
