<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML">
<section>
  <title>Data representation formats in CellML</title>
  <para>
    The following data representation formats are defined for use in this specification:
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A CellML identifier:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
SHALL be a sequence of Unicode characters.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
SHALL NOT contain any characters except basic Latin alphanumeric characters and basic Latin underscores.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
SHALL contain one or more basic Latin alphabetic characters.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
SHALL NOT begin with a European numeric character.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
SHALL, when comparing two identifiers, be considered identical to another
identifier if and only if both identifiers have identical sequences of
Unicode character codes.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A positive integer string:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
SHALL be a base 10 representation of a positive integer.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
SHALL consist entirely of European numeric characters.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          An integer string:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
SHALL be a base 10 representation of an integer.
              </para>
              <para>
When the integer being represented is negative, SHALL consist of the Basic Latin
hyphen-minus character U+002D, followed by the positive integer string
representation of the absolute value of the integer.
              </para>
              <para>
When the integer being represented is positive, SHALL consist of the positive
integer string representation of the integer.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A basic real number string:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
SHALL be a base 10 representation of a real number.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Where the number is negative, SHALL begin with the Basic Latin
hyphen-minus character U+002D as the sign indicator.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
MAY contain a single decimal point separator, which SHALL be the basic
Latin full stop character U+002E.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Other than the sign indicator and the decimal point separator, SHALL consist
only of European numeric characters.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A real number string:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <!-- Note for annotators: No requirement for the real number to
                     be normalised was included here.
                  -->
SHALL be a base 10 representation of a real number
<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <mml:mrow>
    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
    <mml:mrow>
      <mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
      <mml:mo>&#xD7;<!-- times --></mml:mo>
      <mml:msup>
        <mml:mn>10</mml:mn>
        <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
      </mml:msup>
    </mml:mrow>
  </mml:mrow>
</mml:math>, where s is the significand, a real number, and e is the
exponent, an integer.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The representation of the number SHALL be the representation of the significand
followed immediately by the representation of the exponent.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The significand SHALL be represented as a basic real number string.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
If the exponent is zero, the exponent MAY be represented by an
empty string, or MAY be represented according to the following rule. If the
exponent is non-zero, it MUST be represented according to the following rule.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
An exponent SHALL be represented by an exponent separator character, followed
by the integer string representation of the exponent's value. The exponent
separator character SHALL be either the Unicode Basic Latin character 'E' or
the Unicode Basic Latin character 'e'.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </para>
</section>
