<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML">
<section id="encapsulation-element">
  <title>The encapsulation element information item</title>
  <para>
    Encapsulation element information items (referred to in this specification as
    encapsulation elements) are element information items in the CellML 1.2
    namespace with local name equal to encapsulation.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Specific information items</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every encapsulation element MUST contain one or more component_ref elements
          (<xref linkend="component-ref-element" />).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="group-element">
    <title>Forwards and backwards compatibility</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Group element information items (referred to in this specification as
          group elements) are element information items in the CellML 1.1
          namespace with local name equal to group. CellML 1.2 processing software
          MUST accept both group elements in accordance with the rules below and
          encapsulation components, but SHOULD generate only the CellML 1.1
          group element form.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Relationship reference element information items (referred to in this
          specification as relationship_ref elements) are element information
          items in the CellML 1.1 namespace with local name equal to relationship_ref.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every group element MUST contain one or more relationship_ref elements.
          A group element SHOULD be silently ignored unless it contains one or more
          relationship ref_elements which meet the following criteria:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                It contains an attribute in the empty namespace with local name
                relationship and value "encapsulation".
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                It does not contain a name attribute in the empty namespace.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
          A group element MAY contain one or more component_ref elements. In
          the case where the group element is not silently ignored according
          to the rules above, these component_ref elements SHALL be treated as
          if they appeared inside an encapsulation element.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
