<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML">
<section>
  <title>General matters</title>
  <section>
    <title>CellML and XML</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Every CellML Document SHALL be represented in an XML document which conforms with
the well-formedness requirements of the XML 1.0 specification <xref linkend="XML"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
In this document, the remaining provisions relating to CellML Documents shall be
interpreted as being constraints on the XML Information Set represented by that
CellML Document.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Equivalent CellML Documents</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Two CellML Documents shall be equivalent if one can be transformed to another by
making zero or more of the following changes:
        </para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Changing the representation the XML file in ways which
do not change the XML Information Set represented.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Adding, removing, and/or modifying comment information items.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Changing (inserting, removing, and/or modifying) one or more namespace
information items, and/or modifying the prefix of one or more information
items, without changing the namespace that any information item is in.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The following paragraph applies only to character information items which are
the direct child of an element information element in a CellML namespace, or in
the MathML or RDF namespace.
            </para>
            <para>
Inserting or removing character information items that consist entirely of
whitespace characters, changing the number of whitespace characters in such
an information item, or changing the number of whitespace characters at the
beginning or end of a character information item.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Processing Software MUST treat CellML Documents which are equivalent
according to the above rules in an identical fashion.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Use of the CellML namespaces</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Documents MUST NOT contain any element or attribute information items in a
CellML namespace, except as permitted in this specification.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Documents MUST NOT contain any character information items which are
children of element information items in a CellML namespace, except as
permitted in this specification.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Processing Software SHOULD NOT attempt to process CellML Documents which
contain information items in a CellML namespace other than the CellML 1.1
or CellML 1.2 namespaces.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
