<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML">
<section>
  <title>General matters</title>
  <section>
    <title>CellML and XML</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Every CellML Infoset SHALL be represented in an XML document that conforms with
the well-formedness requirements of the XML 1.0 specification <xref linkend="XML"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
In this document, the remaining provisions relating to CellML Infosets shall be
interpreted as being constraints on the XML Information Set represented by that
CellML Infoset.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Equivalent CellML Infosets</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Two CellML Infosets shall be equivalent if one can be transformed to another by
making zero or more of the following changes:
        </para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Changing the representation the XML file in ways that
do not change the XML Information Set represented
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Adding, removing, and/or modifying comment information items.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Changing (inserting, removing, and/or modifying) one or more namespace
information items, and/or modifying the prefix of one or more information
items, without changing the namespace that any information item is in.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The following paragraph applies only to character information items for which all
ancestor element information items are in the CellML, the MathML or the
RDF namespace.
            </para>
            <para>
Inserting or removing character information items that consist entirely of
whitespace characters, changing the number of whitespace characters in such
an information item, or changing the number of whitespace characters at the
beginning or end of a character information item.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Processing Software MUST treat CellML Infosets that are equivalent
according to the above rules in an identical fashion.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Character information items</title>
    <para>
      An element information item in the CellML namespace MUST NOT contain any
      character information items, except for character information items that
      consist entirely of whitespace characters.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Use of namespaces</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Infosets MUST NOT contain any element or attribute information items,
except as permitted in this specification.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Infosets MUST NOT contain any character information items that are
children of element information items in a CellML namespace, except as
permitted in this specification.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Processing Software SHOULD NOT attempt to process CellML Infosets that
contain information items in a CellML namespace other than the CellML 1.2 namespaces,
unless they have been designed to support the version of CellML corresponding to the
namespace.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Infosets MUST NOT contain any element information items in the RDF
namespace, unless:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
the element information item or one of its ancestors is an element information
item in the RDF namespace, with local name <literal>RDF</literal> (the RDF element information
item), and,
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
the RDF element information item forms the top-level of a valid
RDF/XML tree, per production 7.2.9 in <xref linkend="RDF-XML"/>.
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Infosets MUST NOT contain any element information items in the MathML
namespace, unless:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
the element information item or one of its ancestors is an element information
item in the MathML namespace, with local name <literal>math</literal> (the math element information
item), and,
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
the math element information item forms the top-level of a valid
MathML tree, as described in <xref linkend="MathML"/>.
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Extension information items</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Infosets MAY contain zero or more element or attribute information items
in an extension namespace (extension information items), as children of CellML
Information Items.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Information items in the empty namespace, that appear as children of extension element information items, SHALL also be treated as extension information items.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
Extension information items MAY contain extension information items as their
children. In addition, extension elements MAY contain presentation MathML
children. For the avoidance of doubt, it is noted that extension information
items MAY also contain any other information items not disallowed
by this specification or a referenced normative specification.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Processing Software MUST NOT raise an error solely because it encounters
an unrecognised extension element.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Processing Software that reads CellML and then writes a modified
version back out SHOULD preserve unrecognised extension information items when
the parent information item is not modified.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
CellML Processing Software MUST NOT allow the mathematical interpretation of a
CellML Model to be altered by any information present in extension information
items.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Identifiers</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Any element information item in the CellML namespace MAY contain an
          attribute information item with name id, in the CellML Metadata
          Namespace. This attribute information item SHALL be treated as
          having attribute type ID, as defined in section 3.3.1 of
          <xref linkend="XML" />.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Specific information items</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A specific information item is an information item that is not:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                a comment information item, or,
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                a character information item, or,
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                an extension information item or a descendant of such an information item, or,
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                a namespace information item.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Specific information items MUST NOT appear in a CellML Infoset except where
          explicitly allowed by this specification, or where allowed by a
          normative specification referenced by this specification.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The order in which specific information items appear as children of
          an element information item defined in this specification SHALL NOT
          affect the interpretation of the CellML Model.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>RDF Element Information Items</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every element information item in the CellML namespace MAY contain
          zero or more RDF Element Information Item children.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          An RDF Element Information Item SHALL be an element item in the RDF
          namespace, with local name <literal>RDF</literal> (the RDF element information item), and
          MUST form the top-level of a valid RDF/XML tree, per production
          7.2.9 in <xref linkend="RDF-XML"/>, and SHALL be a child of an
          element information item in the CellML namespace.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          CellML Processing Software MUST NOT allow the mathematical
          interpretation of a CellML Model to be altered by any information
          present in RDF data.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The "set of all RDF triples" associated with a CellML Infoset SHALL
          refer to the union of all sets of RDF triples produced by parsing all
          the RDF Element Information Items according to the RDF/XML specification.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Two CellML Infosets that differ only by the addition, removal, or
          modification of RDF Element Information Items (or Information Items
          descended from them), but that have the same set of all RDF triples,
          SHALL be termed RDF-equivalent CellML Infosets.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          CellML Processing Software MUST NOT treat RDF-equivalent CellML
          Infosets differently.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
