<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML">
<section id="unit-element">
  <title>The unit element information item</title>
  <para>
    Unit element information items (referred to in this specification as
    unit elements) are element information items in the CellML 1.2
    namespace with local name equal to unit, and with a units element as their parent.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Specific information items</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every unit element MUST contain a units attribute information item
          in the empty namespace. The value of the units attribute MUST be a
          valid units reference, as defined in <xref linkend="units-reference"/>.
          The units element inclusion digraph SHALL be a conceptual digraph
          defined for the purpose of the constraint in this paragraph, and
          which contains one node for every units element in the CellML Model. The
          units element inclusion digraph SHALL contain an arc from
          units element A to units element B if and only if units element A
          contains a unit element with units attribute value that is a
          units reference to units element B. The value of the units attribute
          MUST NOT be such that the units element inclusion digraph contains
          one or more cycles.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A unit element MAY contain any of the following attribute information
          items in the empty namespace:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The prefix attribute. If present, the value of the attribute
                MUST meet the constraints specified in
                <xref linkend="interpretation-of-units"/>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The offset attribute. If present, the value of the attribute
                MUST be a real number string. If the attribute is present and
                has value other than a real number string representing 0,
                then this unit element MUST NOT have any sibling
                unit elements, and the value of the exponent attribute, if
                present, MUST be a real number string representing 1.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The multiplier attribute. If present, the value of the attribute
                MUST be a real number string.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The exponent attribute. If present, the value of the attribute
                MUST be a real number string.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
