<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML">
<section id="variable-element">
  <title>The variable element information item</title>
  <para>
    Variable element information items (referred to in this specification as
    variable elements) are element information items in the CellML 1.2
    namespace with local name equal to variable, and which appear as a child
    of a component element.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Specific information items when element in the CellML 1.2 namespace</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every variable element MUST have each of the following attribute
          information item in the empty namespace:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The name attribute. The value of the name attribute MUST be a
                valid CellML Identifier. The value of the name attribute MUST
                NOT be identical to the name attribute on any sibling variable
                element.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The type attribute. The primary specification does not place any restrictions
                on the value of the type attribute, but secondary specifications SHOULD
                define the types supported in that secondary specification.
              </para>
              <para>
                A type attribute value of real SHALL be interpreted as indicating that the
                variable is real valued. A type attribute value of boolean SHALL be interpretated
                as indicating that there are two possible values, true and false.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every variable element MAY contain one or more of the following attribute
          information items in the empty namespace:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The public_interface attribute. If the attribute is present, it
                MUST have value yes or no.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The private_interface attribute. If the attribute is present, it
                MUST have value yes or no.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The initial_value attribute. If the attribute is present, it MUST
                meet the requirements described in
                <xref linkend="initial-value-interpretation"/>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The units attribute. If the attribute is present, the value MUST be a
                valid CellML Identifier, and MUST meet the constraints described
                in <xref linkend="units-on-variables" />. This attribute MUST be present
                if the type attribute has the value real.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
